A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Higher Education and Research Division, Program Staff Files FA546
Rockefeller Archive Center
- PAYE (Pay-As-You-Earn), 1969-1972; III
  - PAYE Project -- Statement -- "Pay As You Earn" by Marshall Robinson, [1971] (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - PAYE Project -- Trustees Meeting -- Memos Re: Meeting, Income Programs, Jan 28-29, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - PAYE Project -- Washington Report -- Correspondence with Politicians, Memos Re: Contacts, Report, Oct 23, 1970-Jan 29, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - PAYE -- Yale University -- Educational, Jan 4, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - PAYE -- Yale University -- Meeting Between FF and Yale Trustees -- Minutes, Dec 19, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - PAYE -- Yale University -- Meeting Notes, Memo, Background, Nov 30, 1970-Jan 16, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - PAYE Responses -- A, Mar-Aug 1971 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - PAYE Responses -- B, Mar-Jun 1971 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - PAYE Responses -- C, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - PAYE Responses -- D -- Includes Memos on William Margeson Plan, Feb-Aug 1971 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - PAYE Responses -- I, Mar 8-May 17, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - PAYE Responses -- N, Mar 1971 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - PAYE Responses -- O, Apr-Sep 1971 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - PAYE Responses -- P, Feb-Apr 1971 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - PAYE Responses -- R, Feb-Sep 1971 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - PAYE Responses -- R -- Correspondence, Memo Re: SUNY Old Westbury, Mar-Jul 1971 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - PAYE Responses -- W, Jan-Feb 1971 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - PAYE -- Triffen, Nicholas -- Law -- Legal Issues, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - PAYE -- Triffen, Nicholas -- Memos Re: Borrowing Time, Deferred Income Loans, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - PAYE -- Triffen, Nicholas -- Memo Re: Status Report on Student Advance Income System (SAIS) Participants, Dec 7, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - PAYE -- Triffen, Nicholas -- Notes on Meetings, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Peat, Marwick, Mitchell & Co. -- Study Results, May 25-Jun 30, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - (University of) Pennsylvania -- Memo Re: Meeting with Financial Aid and Admission Directors, Mar 2, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Portland State University -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Site Visit, Parent Survey, PAYE, Apr-Sep 1971 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Program for Research and Investment in Medical Education (PRIME) -- Report and Related Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Stanford University Business School -- Correspondence Re: Site Visit, Progress Report, PAYE, Feb-May 1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Stanford University Medical School -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Transcript Re: Financing Proposal, Jan-Jul 1970 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Stanford University -- General -- Memoranda Re: Visit, Student Loan Questionnaire, Progress Report, Feb-Sep 1971 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - St. John's College (Santa Fe) -- Correspondence Re: PAYE Research, May-Sep 1971 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - St. Louis University -- Correspondence Re: PAYE Project, Dec 1970-Jul 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Student Survey Questionnaire Preliminary Results -- MSI -- Correspondence and Memoranda, Jun 14-Sep 21, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Student Survey Background -- Memoranda and Report, Jun-Sep 1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - SUNY at Albany and Buffalo -- Correspondence Re: Seminar, etc., Jul 1970-Sep 1971 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - VTL -- Correspondence Re: Variable Term Student Loans, Jan-Jul 1971 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - VTL -- Correspondence Re: Variable Term Loan Model, Jan-Jul 1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Yale -- Current -- Transcript, Correspondence and Background Re: Tuition Deferment Plan, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Yale -- General Correspondence Re: Tuition Postponement, PAYE, etc., 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Science and Engineering, 1954-1970; IV
  These files, organized alphabetically by subject, were created by Carl Borgmann as head of the Science and Engineering program and as Advisor on Science and Technology. They include background on the development of the Foundation program in Science and Engineering and the eventual decision to phase it out. The Foundation's support for an engineering residency program and support for "Negro Schools" are extensively documented.
  - Advisor on Science and Technology -- Correspondence, Memoranda Re: Site Visits, Proposed Grant Reviews, etc. (Colorado, Australia), 1966-1967 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Advisor on Science and Technology -- Memoranda Re: Undergraduate Computer Use, Atmospheric Science Grants, etc., 1962-1967 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Astronomy -- Report, Memorandum, Background on Possible Ford Foundation Support for Radio Telescopes, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Bundy, McGeorge -- Letter to Senator Harris Re: Science and Technology Policy, May 21, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Bundy, McGeorge -- Scientists' Advice -- Memoranda Re: Science Service, Foundation Mission, Nov 25, 1968 - Jul 29, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Consultant Reports Re: Science and Engineering Program, 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Course Development Grants -- List with Grant Descriptions, Jan 15, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Deddario Committee -- Borgman Statement before the House of Representatives Sub-Committee on Science, Research and Development of the Committee on Science and Astronautics, 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Development of Ford Foundation Program in Science and Engineering -- Report, Interviews, Summary Memoranda (1 of 2), Dec 15, 1954 - Apr 5, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Development of Ford Foundation Program in Science and Engineering -- Consultants Preliminary Report, Site Visits, Board of Trustees Outline Report, etc. (2 of 2), 1956-1959 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Education Technology Labs -- Memoranda Re: Deafness Work, Dec 31, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Gordon Research Conference -- Santa Barbara -- Correspondence and Background Info, Jan 28 - 31, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Student Loan Program -- Reports, Memoranda, Survey Information, 1960-1969 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Grants -- Descriptive Categories -- Financial Lists, Nov 17, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Negro Schools -- Fisk University -- Department Reports to the Ford Foundation, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Negro Schools -- Ford Foundation Internal Papers Re: Negro Education and FF Policy Development, 1963-1966 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Negro Schools -- Negro Education -- Memorandum by James W. Armsey, Dec 30, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Negro Schools -- North Carolina Teachers Association -- Correspondence Re: Visit, Background on Organization, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Negro Schools -- Paper, Memoranda, Planning Budget, 1964-1966 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Negro Schools -- Papers -- Southern Preparatory Center, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Negro Schools -- Speech -- "The Right to Knowledge" Address by Henry Heald to the American Alumni Council Re: Negro Education, Jul 12, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Negro Schools -- Visits and Interviews -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Southern Preparatory Center, etc., 1966 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Practitioner Teachers -- Correspondence re: Survey of Deans, etc., 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Publicity -- Articles on the Ford Foundation Engineering Residency Program, with Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Report to Advisory Board Re: Engineering Residencies, Nov 13, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Report on Need for More Science Engineering Centers by L.E. Grinter (separated), 1956 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Residency Program -- ASEE -- Correspondence Re: Takeover of Ford Foundation Program, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Residency Program -- Description and Application Form, Apr 1966 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Residency Program -- FAPs / Grant Action, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Residency Program -- O'Brien, M.P. -- Correspondence Re: Adjunct Professors of Engineering, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Residency Program -- Office File -- Correspondence Re: Program Administration, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Residency Program -- Operational Information File -- Memoranda and Background Re: Program Implementation, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Residency Program -- Program Description, Survey, Selection Criteria, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Residency Program -- Sample Industry Letters, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Residency Program -- TIAA Payments -- Grant Information, 1967-1970 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Review of Grants -- Oceanographic and Atmospheric Science, Nov 1969 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Science and Engineering Docket Items, Aug 19, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Science and Engineering Program Evaluation Study -- Special Committee Agenda, Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Science and Engineering Program -- Phasing Out -- Memorandum, Oct 21, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Site Visit Reports -- University of Arizona and University of Waterloo, May 10, 1966-May 15, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Surveys -- Engineering Faculty -- Memorandum and Survey Information, 1963-1970 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Surveys -- Engineering Faculty Study, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Surveys -- Forgivable Loan Graduates, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Surveys -- Forgivable Loan Recipients, Sep 1963 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Surveys -- Summer Institutes on Effective Teaching, 1963-1966 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Surveys -- Undergraduate Engineering Education, Jun 1963 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Transportation -- MIT Transportation Research Memoranda, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Abel Amaya Correspondence, 1970-1975; V
  This series consists of Dr. Amaya's correspondence with grantees and his record of site visits. His files, organized alphabetically by subject, primarily reflect his work with Chicano education.
  - American Association of Community and Junior Colleges Convention -- Invitation Letter, Memorandum Re: Training Program, Dec 28, 1973 - Mar 18, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Arizona State University -- Teacher Preparatory Program -- Correspondence and Memorandum Re: Funding Requirement, 1970-1973 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Crystal City Committee for Rural Democracy -- Correspondence Re: Proposal, Memoranda Re: Site Visit, Jan-May 1973 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Crystal City Internship Program -- Correspondence, Memorandum Re: Site Visit, Jan-May 1973 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Deganiwidah-Quetzalcoatl University -- Memoranda Re: Trip, Possible Ford Foundation Support, Background, 1973-1975 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Martinee, Yaya -- Chicanos in Higher Education Study -- Correspondence Re: Funding, Amaya Leaving the Ford Foundation, Mar-Jun 1975 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Native Americans -- Correspondence and Memorandum, List Re: Inter-Foundation Discussion, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - New Mexico Highlands University -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Meeting Notes, Site Visit, 1972-1974 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Social Science Research Council -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Spanish Ancestry Committee Meeting, Jul-Oct 1974 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Visit Reports -- Memoranda Re: Site Visits, 1973-1975 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Peter E. de Janosi, 1966-1972; VI
  This series includes Dr. de Janosi's chronological files for 1972, which contain grant-related correspondence and records of site visits. A separate file contains memoranda related to Higher Education and Research Division staff meetings. There are also some of his subject files, organized alphabetically.
  - Chronological File, Jan 1972 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Chronological File, Feb 1972 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Chronological File, Mar 1972 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Chronological File, Apr 1972 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Chronological File, May 1972 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Chronological File, Jun 1972 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Chronological File, Jul 1972 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Chronological File, Aug 1972 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Chronological File, Sep 1972 (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Chronological File, Oct 1972 (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Chronological File, Nov 1972 (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Chronological File -- Grant Correspondence, Site Visits, etc., Dec 1972 (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe -- Papers -- Agenda, LAC, A&P (1 of 3), Feb 24-25, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe -- Papers -- Discussion/Background (2 of 3), Feb 24-25, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe -- Papers -- Social Science Conference Papers (3 of 3), 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Financing of Traditionally Black Institutions -- Memoranda Re: Data, Site Visit, Fellowships, etc., 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Germany -- Economics and Economists -- Memoranda Re: University Site Visits, 1967-1968 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Germany -- University Development -- Memoranda Re: German Universities, Sep 17-Dec 6, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Greece -- General -- Report on Greek Higher Education, Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Education, 1969-1971 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Higher Education and Research (HER) Future Program Direction -- Memoranda, Jan 17-Feb 11, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Higher Education and Research (HER) Staff Meetings -- Memoranda Re: Meeting Minutes, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Higher Education and Research (HER) in Western Europe -- Ford Foundation Report on Shrinking Gap, 1970-1971 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Israel -- General -- Memoranda on Ford Foundation Programming, Trip Report, Aug-Sep 1971 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Israeli Foundations Trustees -- Memoranda Re: IFT, Grant Request, 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Japan -- Economics -- Economists -- Memoranda Re: Economists, etc., 1966-1967 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Japan -- General -- Memoranda and Report on Japan Education Reform, 1967-1971 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Spain -- General -- Memoranda Re: Fellowships, University Development, Trip, 1968-1971 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Sweden -- Social Sciences -- General -- Correspondence and Notes Re: Stockholm Trip, Feb-Mar 1971 (Box 16, Folder 16)
- Corinne Kirchner, 1956-1969; VII
  Corinne Kirchner's files appear to have originated in the Office of the Secretary. Organized alphabetically, they contain research for fact sheets about the Ford Foundation, a faculty salary study, and a survey of fellowships and scholarships. There are also memoranda about general support grants and the grant analysis unit.
  - About the Ford Foundation -- Reports and Fact Sheets Used for Publication Revision, 1960-1966 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Salaries -- University Finance Report, Press Release and Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Support for Increased Salaries, 1956-1967 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships -- Ford Foundation Study/Survey Memoranda, 1957-1963 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - General Support Grants -- Memoranda, Background Data and Analysis, 1963-1969 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Grant Analysis Unit -- Memoranda Re: Establishment and Improvement of Unit, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - "In Praise of Candor" -- Remarks of McGeorge Bundy to the American Council on Education, Oct 13, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Edward J. Meade, 1958-1972; VIII
  Organized alphabetically by subject, Dr. Meade's files focus on educational issues, including desegregation and support for disadvantaged minorities, studies on school drop-outs, and support for gifted youth and leadership programs.
  - Assessment -- Ford Foundation Press Release Re: ETS, Dec 30, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Desegregation -- Sandwich Seminar Think Piece, Oct 19, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Disadvantaged -- Lists of Ford Foundation Grants for "American Negros" and "American Indians", 1966-1971 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Drop-outs -- Ford Foundation Press Release Re: Studies on High School Dropouts, 1963-1964 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Enrichment Programs for Disadvantaged Students -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Programs, 1967-1968 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Financing -- List of Ford Foundation Grants, Writings on Education Finance Reform, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Gifted -- Memorandum and Lists of Ford Foundation Grants for Gifted Education, 1958-1967 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Leadership Programs -- Consortium -- Ford Foundation Press Release and Programs List, Jan 26, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Parks, Educational -- Site Visit to East Orange Pilot School, Jan 15, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Resources and the Environment -- Press Release, Grant Recommendation, May-Oct 1971 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Roper Report on Ford Foundation Education Program, Apr 1959 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Teacher Education -- Memoranda on Ford Foundation Programs, Grant Lists, Background, 1960-1972 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Technology -- Instructional Technology Report, List, Memorandum, 1969-1971 (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Visitations -- Memorandum and List Re: Travel and Study Awards, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Vocational Education Report, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 21)